right hello everyone my
name is shin and this is
paula hi everyone how are
you i hope you're having
a good first tour of this
master maybe even more
closer to the earth but
anyway who is counting
welcome to the cs6300
subway development process
of this hour so let me
see this is week seven
and this week students
are supposed to
watch lecture P3O4
unified software process
and P4L1 testing
general concept.
This week students are supposed
to submit two different
submissions on well two
different submissions
one is group project
deliverable 2 which is
So one member of the team
will submit on Canvas and
the remaining team members
should at least double
-check because this is the
shared responsibility.
If the team forgets, then
everybody will be affected.
So yeah, it's one
person doing, but the
other should be double
-checked as well.
That is the GPD tool, right?
And the other is individual
assessment or design.
This one, each
individual student
should be submitting
on Grayscope,
not on Canvas, on Grayscope.
And it is your own that
you evaluate other team
members, teammates from GPD,
the one when you were doing
design and discussion.
Remember,
do not forget you have two
different submissions
this week.
That's pretty much,
we are now in a
second level of a
group project, so I
think most of the
question is for that.
Let's go to the first question.
So the question is, I
was curious whether there
were sample more
detailed direction we can
use for deliverables in
group deliverable two.
It's the question here.
And then it's hard
for me to understand
what level of detail we
need to provide without
samples like that.
and actually if if you
follow that um that link
example uh for each template
then there is already
one um there are there
are two answers from the
staff and um are not so
these these are samples
for well project plan
use case and test plan
there are some other
templates that we include
in the group project
as well but these are
also good one as for
whether it is sufficient
enough then I think
Paula has answered this
multiple multiple times
in previous office hours.
It's by balance. And sometimes
you know it when you see
it. Sometimes if you put
your shoes in another team
member who just received
these documents or these
artifacts, whether they can
get started and resume or
continue, or they don't have
enough information or they just
get confused by a lot of
uh tmi and then they just
put put everything into ai
and say summarize this for me
but yeah um paula do you
have yeah no yeah i no i just
really i think there are
a couple of key things uh
in the deliverable descriptions
because when i saw the
question i went back reading
it and there are things
like you know imagine you're
the ta is grading and he's
reading it and he's there
is written right like he
doesn't have to ask themselves
questions so are we are we
expecting you to write 50
pages of material no of
course not but if you are
coherent you follow the structure
of the templates and and
and and and you and people
that read and haven't written
them understand and things
are coherent with each
other then then you are on
the right track right so uh
this is really a big part
of of the work right try to
understand what is enough
and and what is too much uh
and so it's uh it's try for
a second to look at this
from outside and somebody is
reading it and you look at
your project plan would they
understand how i will carry
out this project yes or
no i mean if the answer is
oh here is not that very
clear who does what then
maybe no right and so you need
to clarify something if here
you say oh i fell asleep
when i was rereading my
project plan maybe you put too
much right i fall asleep
many times when i reread my
papers that's not a very
good sign but but this is the
point right each of these
documents has to do something
and so reread them try to
you know try to distance
yourself from the document
and the fact that you know the
rationale why you wrote it
because when your TAs read
them to grade them they are
not in your head so they
read what is written and
if it's enough they will
understand if it's not then
it's the moment in which you're
losing points and there
are mismatching so remember
what each each of the document
is supposed to be doing
follow the template make
sure that all the section
are there my suggestion you
know i come from classical
study before studying
engineering so i study
latin and greek that
people might think that is
completely useless but i
think instead i've learned a
lot because the things that
i do when i read things
that i have to do i i light
all the main points and
i go back to that to make
sure i cover all of them
so sometimes the description
of your assignment
and deliverable are are
long but they're not long
unintentionally each piece
is kind of a guide for you
to do it right so i think
you have all the answer
in deliverable too for for
answering this question
i hope this helps
okay thanks fauna and
actually that is the
single question we have
at until this moment
um meanwhile anything um
interesting in the academy
in academia i don't know
i don't know it also
happens that we have this
office hour when I'm working
on something because
so it's a deadline very
soon so I'm working on on
a paper on interview script
do you know what an
interview script is yes I
guess so but anyway so now
to find if human or LLMs
are better to review
interview script do you want
to know the end of the
story do you want a spoiler
on this story it becomes
a Turing test already?
No, actually humans are better.
So LLM are more comprehensive.
It's very interesting
because we did this empirical
study and of course like
LLMs are more comprehensive
in finding things and in
their feedback but the people
that receive the feedback
find it overwhelming and
not that very useful. Which
I find is a very interesting
point because you know we
create all these things
to automatize things and
then but the point is
that if if what we create is
us to be used by human the
real question is is this
is really useful right um
i don't know i'm always so
the since we are waiting
for questions i i want to
say something about the
creator of this course right
so alex of work alex or
so that is the person that
created all the material
that you are talking in all
the classes. I didn't mean
to make it funny, I'm just
Italian, so I do judge
this, sorry. I didn't mean
to just be disrespectful,
but he has worked many years
on automatic debugging and
I think he has this paper
that I recommend to everybody
with Chris Parnin, that I
think now works at University
of North Carolina, but was
a PhD student at Georgia
Tech on this consideration
of, are we really evaluating
automatic debugging tool
in the right way, right?
So the idea of automatic
debugging that I think now
that you're writing code for
this class or also for your
job, you're knowing like
it would be very nice if I
had a tool that when there
is a bug, I click a button
and tell me here is the bug,
fix it. Really for now, what
they do is they're telling
you, oh, the bug is in
this piece of code, right they
take away part of the code
to look and in this study
that they did they say yes
but this is completely
useless like you know we are
battling on this tool saying
this tool give you five
percent this tool give you
two percent this tool give you
yes but two percent of 10
000 line of code is still a
very big number and nobody
if i give you like 100 line
of code and say oh the bug
is here we'll just look at
those because this is not
how our developer work you
follow your path right and so
it was about what is really
what would be really useful
from things that that i
mean of course if we if we
are able to perfectly identify
the bug that would be
perfect but since we are not
what is really useful for
developer so i think that
this is this is a very
important question every time we
develop a tool that other
people will use it's not just
how precise it is, how
correct it is. I mean, of
course, if you're developing
a critical safety software,
just please make sure it's
perfectly safe and correct.
But there is also, if instead
it's something that is
in human interaction, the
perception of the users and
how they consider it useful
is really very important.
So anyway, see, I'm
very entertaining.
I'm talking about
the correctness.
So, I mean, this discourse,
later on in this course,
we have a lot of testing.
We have black forecasting,
white forecasting,
somewhere in between black
forecasting as well. And
then something that we
mentioned, I think, but
not teaching in this course
is formal verification.
And the thing is formal
verification is the holy
grail, most because it is
the final frontier and also
because it is too hard to
achieve and it's reserved
for only the most critical
like nuclear or aerospace.
But the thing is
right now because
with the formal verification
it's either we can see
that whether we have the
formal verification or not
And if we have it, we can
easily verify whether
everything is correct, right?
Is there anything in
the academia right
now to apply AI
agents into better or
faster having the
formal verification?
So it's a little more
complicated than this, right?
because yes so like I
think when you talk about
formal verification you you
have to you have to separate
in like formal methods
tool that try to achieve
it all and so requires
human intervention because
you know like if you take
all the complexity of your
code and whatever property
you want to express this
become a problem that
you cannot solve fully
automatically and so there
there is this need of gigantic
human expertise or things
in which you abstract
some details away and then
you can do it all automatic.
So I don't know, that
would be the difference
between theory improving
and model checking, right?
The model checking is
something that you have a model
of your system in which you
abstract away some of your
detail or a model of your
code or your code that get
abstracted away automatically.
You write the property,
you click a button and the
model checker tells you yes
the property holds or no
look at the counterexample
right but then with some
abstraction so it's never 100
and then theory improver is
like you really like try to
prove things and then there
are tools that help you to
do some of these but the
human need to make certain
decision or certain pieces
the problem is that up to now
up to a little bit before
i mean these are very
complicated things that you
were saying and the tools are
really unusable right so the
barrier to enter into this
field or for people to apply
it or to get particularly
enthusiastic about
it is very there is
a big step right
it's very high like
I work I mean I did my PhD
thesis on model checking
so but it's like it's not
you know this topic that
the other PhD students want
to chat with you about.
But now they are doing a
lot of attempt to try to see
how AI can help to make
them more accessible or to
guide some of this process
automatically. They are still
iterative. But so if we go
back, for instance, right,
to what we were talking a
couple of office hours ago,
you know, like a big
piece of this is that
how do you write the
property that you want
to be verified? You
write it in logic and
logic is not the best
friend of human being.
So there has been, I
was reading a few days,
a few weeks ago, this paper,
very interesting in which
they were trying to,
you know, like I do the
other way around because now
I work in requirements,
but they were trying to
automatize the fact that
you write your specification
directly in logic so the
human doesn't have to know,
right? Right. But the
automatic tool, even the more
advanced to now, they reach
maximum correctness of 50
percent. And with the human
in the loop, 80 percent,
which is terrifying if you
think about this, because
you are using formal
verification or model checking
or whatever, whatever kind
of formal verification
you're using, model checking,
to do something using a
property that has so much
chances to be wrong and and
i think and i think you
know i think in um the
consensus is that to have
this tool to be uh supporting
the reason in the reasoning
because if you try you know
like you use formal
verification in any of its form
uh when you really need
to be sure about certain
properties right because
it's a software that run on a
medical device it's a
software that run on a plane,
anything that, you know,
it cannot really fail. And
so if you remove, and there
are a lot of studies, very,
very interesting that
shows like, you know, and
they're not recent, they're
not about LLMs, right? Like
there are studies from the
80s that were saying that
basically if you start
automatizing certain process,
people lose their competence
and then become like they
introduce mistake so you
know like you can you call
things with different name
and they can do different
things but they are similar
problems and and so in this
field in which the correctness
and so it's not oh I'm
good at 90% so it's fine
I'm happy like this not the
10% in a medical device you
know think about that if
the medical if there are 10
% chances that your medical
device doesn't respect the
property that save your
life i don't know i don't
know so there is this kind
of consensus to try not to
take away uh the you know
the human input and so there
is um it's it's it's more
about make a formal method
usable like more accessible
to a larger pool of people
rather than you know
substitute the competencies
yeah cool all right um i do
have some follow-up on that
but we do also have question
here so let's get back
to the question um we're
trying to define team roles
for d3 and d4 but in practice
it seems likely that on
four of us will contribute
of course on areas rather
than having strictly separated
responsibilities is it
acceptable if roles are
defined primarily for
coordination purposes where actual
work is more collaborative
and overlapping are you
expecting clearly isolated
ownership per role well um
this is exactly what what
we want to um to to teach
is that is a collaborative
and it is it's not like hand
off and then you do you
do you if the project fail
is and it is your area it's
because of your fault right
not not finger pointing
like that so exactly like
you mentioned is more about
uh we have accountability,
responsibility,
and some others like
collaborative or something,
right? So, yes, you can
define the role as the primary
coordination or some,
let's say, accountability.
But, yes,
anybody in the team can and
should collaborate. great.
In the industry, we
call them full-stack
employee or full
-stack team member, but
that is exactly what
you should be doing.
Next question, then is a
link to another ad post?
Project plan has
some generic software
dev activities, but
according to video, the
project plan is
supposed to be indexed
by inception and names
that are on video,
which nomenclature is expected
in the project plan activity.
To the working section,
the access provide
description and trans-criteria,
sit-criteria, I guess.
What activity is
supposed to be, are
these activities supposed
to be traditional
software development
activities,
modeling requirements?
So they can be mapped
together anyway, right?
And if the assignment is
just as simple as copy
and paste from the lecture
to the assignment, it
doesn't assess your
learning. So the naming is
not as important as the
mapping of the description
and also entrance criteria
and exit criteria.
So in short, yeah,
you can use the
inception and others,
but you can also
do the business
modeling, et cetera,
as long as the description
entrance criteria
and exit criteria
covers all needed information,
again, such that if you
hand over this plan to
all the team members, or
if you have a new team
member joining, they
can easily onboard it.
So another logistic
question, do we need to
implement persistence
for the application
data, job offers and
comparison settings,
well, first of all, if it
is defined in the assignment
file instruction, then
of course you have to.
Otherwise, it's up to the team
because this is
implementation detail.
And also persistence here,
it means a lot of things,
right? It can be whether
within the same section, I go
from one page to another page
and go back, whether it's
still there. Or you mean
that after the user opens the
app, close the app and
open again, that's another
case. And sometimes persistence,
even after the user delete
the application and later
install the application.
I believe,
well, I don't want to
answer if I don't remember
100%, but in the past, a
lot of teams get points
deducted because they were
using local persistence
and they did not
initialize it correctly.
that is after the TA
installed the app and opened
the app, it crashed
immediately, and most of the
time it crashed because
SQLite known something,
that is the local
persistent, it's not
initialized correctly.
So remember, if the
team has that kind
of local persistence,
make sure that you initialize
correctly. Most of the time,
the team installs once and
then just keep working on that.
And then they don't
realize the first
initialization is
the problem as well.
Next question, can we
assume that we only need
to support one device time?
Where should we define
supported device
assumption and constraint?
Yes, in assignment
4, I think we
specify pixel 6
or pixel 8, right?
Where should we define
supported device?
That's a good
question. But actually,
in our template, in
our GPT-1 template,
we already have somewhere.
I don't remember the
top of my head right
now. But yes, you should
define all those
assumptions and constraints.
It is in one of the templates.
Okay.
I'm probably waiting
for more questions.
And now I forget what questions
I was trying to
do the follow-up.
i can tell you i was
wondering your opinion i was
talking we were talking
about how ai can help
informal verification um
and so i took for half an
hour and now would be
your turn to say something
well i i am i am always uh
fascinated about that um i
i once used toa plus for a
small part um as the formal
verification but unfortunately
uh during my whole
career i worked mostly in
in startup or basically non
-critical um application so
it's it's not required and
because it's not required then
when when when something is
nice to have it's definitely
mean you won't have it.
You know the only time in
my life I work in the real
world this is how I talk
about my career right there
like you know I think I
think working in academia is
very fascinating because you
talk about with people that
work in the real world
you know like we have our
advisory board all the
collaborators but but when I was I
did a postdoc I was still
in Europe and we brought the
verification we did all
the verification for this
software that was very
fascinating they was checking the
validity of bills like
money like to check if they
are valid or not so there is
this software and they were
checking all certain criteria
that you couldn't you
know this machine has you
know like for to avoid that
people introduce and i was
like if i make some mistake
here it's gonna be a
disaster it's like i was like
it's gonna be like europe
we just crash out of all the
millions of euros and it's
my fault i don't know if i
want to do this like i don't
know give me an example
just just just find somebody
else because you know there
is a piece that you need
to do some you know even
when you say okay this is
a safe obstruction or this
it's a manual proof and you
know people make mistakes
it's just but for now i don't
know we sign a lot of paper
i think it was part of
my contract as postdoc it
lasted a year so and then i
went to and then i work on a
flexible manufacturing
system very fascinating topic
um then then that that
work with the the euro um
monday uh checking uh is it
finally adopted or was it
like um deployed release i
don't know but i mean they
had the machine they had
the contract so i mean i
just had to do the verification
part so like building
the model of the software
like specify just i did a
lot of it was in fact it
was very strange because it
was it was an application
of what i knew as research
but it was not really a
research but you know sometimes
as a postdoc you need
something to pay for stocks
it was uh but it was really
the only time in which
like you know i thought
oh my god if i do some
mistake here i'm happy that
i'm working as a step below
ruin people life okay now i
remember what i was trying
to uh to ask so um right
now uh with the with the
agent the the shift in the
industry is that the the junior
or the fresh engineer has
really hard time because
most of the company um senior
engineers they just they
just manage a team of agents
um so right now uh freshly
graduate our boot camp
student uh code code boot camp
student they they have a
really hard time getting
into into the industry um do
you see the same or difference
in in other like and and
when i say this code boot
camp is like web app and
like come up commodity app
right um but for those high
stack and critical path like
medical um nuclear aerospace
is is the fresh fresh
graduate or junior engineer
or junior people in general
easily being replaced and
then only senior use the
use the AI tools or is more
stable in the I think it's
more stable and I'm actually
I read the see i'm reading
a lot i'm actually want
i'm lying i don't read all
this paper but i i drive a
lot so i create podcasts out
of the papers i want to
read this is just to say uh
but uh so otherwise you
think i'm spending all my day
reading but really i spend
many hours driving so this
is how i read my papers
but um i was reading this
interesting study that actually
is done on the code generated
from a team of agents
right and so i'm curious to
see how it's gonna go on the
long run because apparently
they're not very good in
creating maintainable code
and so you know it's is it
gonna be really cheap to
redo things from scratch
when you cannot maintain them
so uh i i think that so that
certain industry will not
touch at all uh and certain
others will have to roll
back a piece this is not to
say that this is not that
you know agents as part of
the team are not here for
staying but i think at the
end of the day it's like when
you work with a team of people
everybody's do is better
at doing something so i
think that there is still a
lot to know of what they
are good at doing to support
the human in in interaction
right like it's a developing
software is a team effort
because real software is
complicated and so it's
not a single person job and
and and so i think we still
don't know enough so you know
some company just go all
the way and say now I have
a senior manager that does
that because we can afford
it maybe in three years they
realize that this was not
being very convenient but
actually as a you know the
cost that you're saving at
some point they'll happen
now certain other company
because they have certain
process will not take the
risk so it really depends it's
true that you know company
are trying depending on the
company and the kind of
software they are developing
but maintainability is
the concepts we use before
the ai start writing code
right so so what what
what is maintainability
for me it's like uh when
the code is easy to
maintain easy to extend that
is if we if i have a book
i i look at it and i i
can easily see it right
and then easy to extend I
don't have any, well,
solid principle, et cetera.
And then when I want to
extend a new business logic,
I don't have to struggle with
the spaghetti code, right?
But whether it's
maintainable or extendable,
when I myself look at the
code or when a newcomer
look at the code, at
least they will, when they
get a new feature
request, they look at the
code, oh, ****, what is
that? And then, you know,
there is a ***, a metric of how
the code is
maintainable, right?
But now, what if the
code is now written by
an AI agent, of course,
with certain human
approval, right? But
then in the future, the
same code may be extended
by another agent.
So for now, in the study
they did, they're not that
very good at maintaining it
themselves. So it was called
the bad, I don't remember
the title of the paper, I
think it was an ICSI paper
last year, the bad, the
good, the bad and the ugly,
something like a classic,
you know, the title. And it
was a study on code, like
with developers, and so
we're showing what the agents
were good at doing and
what they were not good at
doing. um and um and uh and
it's interesting and this is
why i'm thinking right uh
um that we still need to
know what we can um you know
i i might be wrong right
but i i don't think i will
be alive that i will be a
work a wording with uh
agents can do all the things
without human and i actually
think that uh and i'm at
every level uh but i think
that instead the best use of
this would be to really keep
studying what these agents
are good at supporting
human with you know because
there are also so many things
that we don't like doing
and so if an agent can
support us doing them that's
not bad there are other things
that are very interesting
you know when i was teaching
at the beginning you
know at the beginning of an
academic career you teach
almost everything and so of
course i i actually really
like teaching basic
computer science to you know
not not computer scientists
in which i don't know i was
in an engineering college
so all the engineers had
to learn some coding and i
was telling them you know
you're thinking about coding
like this very difficult
thing but it's about what
you have to say you know you
can know german and if you
have nothing to say for
the question that i i'm
asking you you're not going to
tell it in german but you're
not going to tell it in
english you're not going
to tell it in italian right
and it's the same thing for
code and don't get me wrong
like you know i'm it's
it's true there is an entry
moment for a person that
never opened and never coded
but if you don't know how
to solve the problem it
doesn't really matter that
you understand the syntax of
whatever programming language
so there are pieces you
need to understand the
problem you need to understand
how to solve it in the
paradigm of the language you
have and then then then it's
a translation job and so
and you know maybe if there
is a way which you don't
have to learn uh the minuscule
things that that's nice
it's uh it's definitely
a nice thing but but it's
solving a problem and
conceptually thinking and how to
break it down that's fun
that that gives satisfaction
yeah okay let me take a
look at the uh okay yeah so
there's no other question and
paula i think we can we can
just turn our office hour
into a kind of a podcasting
i was actually thinking
myself start like i just
started i'm just gonna sit
on a sofa next week and like
and um it's just more and
then a microphone i don't know
i'm thinking we are gonna
be transforming memes or
something like that but please
guys don't do it it's just
okay yeah cool i think we
can code it for the night
see you next week yeah see you
thank you all bye
bye thank you bye